A Guide to the Papers of Wilbur Earnest MacClenny, 1789-1949 bulk 1900-1949.
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Wilbur Earnest MacClenny 1789-1949 bulk 1900-1949.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3615
This collection consists of 5000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift on 1950 November 20.
Scope and Content Information
The papers consist of correspondence, 1900-1949, and diaries, 1900-1902, 1935-1940, of MacClenny together with his topical files on the history and genealogy of Suffolk and Nansemond County, Va., and Gates County, N.C.
Religious and military history of the area were his chief interests and there is considerable material on the Christian denomination, its local congregations, the Eastern Virginia Christian Conference, and early leader James O'Kelly. There are also research notes, rosters, and histories of local participation in the Revolution, the War of 1812, the Civil War, the Spanish American War and World War I.
Items of interest include cargo manifests for two ships, 1814 and 1824; arithmetic book, 1826-1828; copies of Civil War diaries, chiefly Union, mentioning local battles; a ledger for Smith and Bigelow, merchants, of Norfolk, 1901; and a report, 1941, on the poll tax and voter registration in Virginia by Ted Dalton, R.K. Gooch, and James P. Woods.
Luther Porter Jackson and George Washington Carver are correspondents.
The collection also contains correspondence, 1922-1924, of Joseph Henry Riddick, executive secretary of the Virginia Literary and Athletic League concerning high school debating tournaments at the University of Virginia.
Contents List
- Corrrespondence
  - Correspondence of Wilbur E. MacClenny 1900-1949, n.d., 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Joseph H. Riddick, Bureau of Extension, University of Virginia 1922-1924, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Joseph H. Riddick, Bureau of Extension, University of Virginia 1922-1924, n.d. (Box 2)
- Topical
  - Churches
    - American Sunday School Associations 1909-1944, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Baptist Churches 1938, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Christian Churches 1926-1944, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Church Officials n.d. (Box 2)
    - Eastern Virginia Christian Conference 1909-1945, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Eastern Virginia Christian Conference: Reports 1926-1949, n.d. (Box 3)
    - Histories and Miscellaneous 1941, n.d. (Box 3)
    - "The Life of Reverend James O'Kelly and Some Facts about the Early History of the Christian Church in the South" by Wilbur Earnest MacClenny n.d. (Box 3)
    - Methodist Churches n.d. (Box 3)
    - North Carolina Conference Churches 1941, n.d. (Box 3)
    - Reverend James O'Kelly: Research Notes 1909-1910, n.d. (Box 3)
    - Prominent Figures 1941-1948, n.d. (Box 4)
    - Regional Movements in Virginia and North Carolina n.d. (Box 4)
    - Religious Education 1938-1947, n.d. (Box 4)
    - Various Denominations 1938-1947, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Genealogy
    - Baker family--Fontaine family 1925, n.d.
    - Bennett family 1944, n.d. (Box 4)
    - Hare family--Pugh family 1925-1938, n.d. (Box 4)
    - Holland family 1923-1939, n.d. (Box 4)
    - Lee family n.d. (Box 5)
    - Norfleet & Hill families 1927-1942, n.d. (Box 5)
    - Rawles family--Yeates family 1922-1932, n.d. (Box 5)
    - Sumner family n.d. (Box 5)
    - Genealogy Notes 1934, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Nansemond County, Virginia and Gates County, North Carolina
    - American Revolution and War of 1812 n.d. (Box 5)
    - Blacks in Nansemond County n.d. (Box 5)
    - Business Papers 1880-1942 (Box 5)
    - Civil War 1902-1914, n.d. (Box 6)
    - Histories of Gates County n.d. (Box 6)
    - Histories of Nansemond County n.d., 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Judicial and Political Papers n.d. (Box 6)
      [including the Report of the Subcommittee for a study of constitutional provisions concerning voting in Virginia of the Virginia Advisory Legislative Council]
    - Land: Patents and Industries n.d. (Box 6)
    - Legal Papers 1832-1944 (Box 7)
    - Manifests of the Cargos of Rising Sun and Three Friends1814, 1824 (Box 7)
    - Military: Roster Commissioned Officers Virginia Volunteers 1921 (Box 7)
    - Military: Rosters 1777-1866 (Box 7)
    - Military: Rosters 1909-1937, n.d. (Box 7)
    - Military: Writings and Histories 1755-1941, n.d. (Box 7)
    - Research Notes n.d., 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Sons of the American Revolution, Virginia Society Papers 1930-1941 (Box 8)
    - Spanish-American War 1941-1947, n.d. (Box 8)
    - Suffolk n.d., 2 folders (Box 8)
    - World War I n.d. (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous and Printed
  - Miscellaneous Research Notes n.d. (Box 8)
  - Photographs and Postcards n.d. (Box 9)
  - Printed: Articles by Wilbur Earnest MacClenny 1911-1937 (Box 9)
  - Printed: Churches 1896-1944, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Printed: Miscellaneous 1789-1944 (Box 9)
  - Printed: War Memorials 1920-1945
- Bound Volumes
  - Biographical Information on James O'Kelly n.d. (Box 10)
  - Cyphering Book kept by Nathaniel Wright 1826-1828 (Box 10)
  - Diaries and Historical Datebooks kept by Wilbur Earnest MacClenny ca. 1935-1940 (Box 10)
  - Diary kept by Wilbur Earnest MacClenny 1900 Jan-1902 Feb (Box 10)
  - Gates County, North Carolina n.d. (Box 10)
  - Lectures Notes kept by Wilbur Earnest MacClenny n.d. (Box 10)
  - Ledger for Smith & Bigelow, merchants of Norfolk, Virginia 1901 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous: Essays and Ledgers 1908-1910, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous: Historical Notes n.d. (Box 11)
  - Nansemond County, Virginia ca. 1928 (Box 11)
  - Nansemond County, Virginia n.d. (Box 11)
  - Nansemond County, Virginia Churches and related n.d. (Box 11)
- Oversize Bound Volumes
  - Scrapbooks containing Nansemond County, Virginia and Gates County, North Carolina histories n.d., 5 volumes (Box 11)